[Music]
Welcome to what's new in server and
database in the 2025 release wave
1. In this session we're going to talk
about four different topics. AL runtime
database stack the web services stack
and reporting. So let's dive into it.
The first enhancement we did in the AL
runtime is a new way you can format
numbers with net formats.
So this only works in auto format
expressions, not in the format function,
but it allows you to do a format string
such as this or with an example here um
with a format string that
returns one way of the of formatting the
number if the value is positive. Here
you can see uh 1050 if the value is
positive. If um the value is negative,
you get the value presented with
parenthesis and if the value is zero,
you get simply a zero
written. This was used if you want to
see examples in uh in the enhancements
of the financial reporting feature where
a user can choose the way they want to
have their negative form numbers
formatted. In the last release wave, we
added support in client URLs to specify
a layout parameter in the URL. And this
then opens the page in different modes
such as analysis mode. And in this
release wave, we follow up with the get
URL AL function. So with two new
overloads of that, so that you can use
that to construct similar URLs that also
use the layout parameter.
For performance, we uh we have an a
feature where you can specify only to
calculate vis visible flow fields on a
page. We are a bit cautious. Uh so uh we
always um think about whether this can
have an impact. So for now you need to
enable this with a feature management
key calculate only visible flow fields
and then you can uh then you can get the
benefits of this. Then later we will
make this the default
value. There's also a new method on
record ref where you can uh now call set
autoc calc fields and this sets which
flow fields should be updated
automatically. If you ever need to take
a copy of the current stack trace from
uh from AL, there's a new property
session information. Stack that will do
this. Make sure that you only use this
sparingly because it it requires a lot
of CPU to do this. So make sure that you
don't uh overdo it. The in the past the
way the only way you could do this was
to throw an exception and then call um
get last error call stack I think it's
called. But now you can just call
session information.core
stack. Then finally if you need to do
any analysis in a telemetry on on open
company whatever happens there u we now
added two new custom dimensions user
type and guest user in telemetry events
2 and 4 RT2 and 4. In the past you would
need to get these from the the events RT
1 and three and then join. So that could
be a very expensive KQL queries to
execute in the database stack. We also
did some improvements. The first one is
faster copy company. This operation is
now up to five times faster especially
if you have a lot of data. Now you still
need to be cautious with copy company.
It can take a lot of locks and
especially uh you don't want people
working in the company. So don't do it
during working hours in a company that's
being used. And also the operation takes
a lot of resources on the server on the
sorry on the database. So uh so bear
that in mind. These things still
apply. If you use the database missing
indexes page, we now have some extra
goodies for you. Um, we have new fields
that will help you answer questions such
as how often would a proposed index be
used or how would it uh improve
performance and then combine these two,
how useful would a proposed index
actually be. The database indexes page
is basically an an wrapper on top of the
uh DM DB missing index details DMV on
SQL Server. And we added these new
fields. Seeks scans average total cost
average impact and estimated benefit. Uh
if you're interested in this topic, go
and read the documentation for from SQL
Server on this DMV and then learn how to
use these new properties with uh with
what we already have to uh to help you
um if you need to do index tuning and
add new keys as it's called in
A. And the final thing for the database
is for on premises. If you use high
availability setups uh such as uh
multi-ubnet failover um you now have a
new option in the uh new server setting
where you can set uh the property enable
SQL multi-ubnet failover to true. And by
doing this the server will generate um
or add new properties to the connection
strings when we when the server connects
and discuss uh data with with SQL
server. Uh by by enabling this your
failover time can uh can drastically be
improved. If you need to use this uh
consult the SQL server documentation on
multi-ubnet
failover. So in the web services stack
we have two new features. The first is a
hardening that uh is coming from the
Microsoft initiative secure future
initiative SFI and uh this is the
largest security hardening projects in
the world. In Business Central, we um we
looked at outgoing calls from HTTP
client and if you call an endpoint and
that endpoint have a ser server
certificate, we now validate whether
that certificate is valid. If not, we
will actually not call the
endpoint. In version 26, you can disable
this hardening behavior. So, so that in
case you have endpoints that needs to be
fixed, uh you can you can disable a
feature management with a with feature
management in this with this key HTTP
server certificate validation and then
um you can can get unblocked but just
note that in the next version in October
2025 this validation will be enforced
and uh you can no longer disable this
hardening in feature management. ment in
case you need to know whether any um
outgoing calls are failing due to this
hardening there's a new telemetry event
RT52 you can see in which environment it
happened in which app in which object
then some uh information about which
certificate it was and the failure
reason for why this validation failed.
So that allows you to troubleshoot
things already now and then hopefully
you will be ready when the when this
validation is enforced in
October. The second feature is
um Microsoft um starting to lock down
the use of UI pages for web services
starting with with SOAP endpoints. So in
this uh wave um we will block UI pages
published by Microsoft as SOAP
endpoints. If you need this feature uh
we have a couple of hundred uh tenants
or customers who have this enabled. You
can still go to feature management and
uh and have this behavior disable. So
web services on UI pages it's default is
a enabled means that these endpoints uh
are blocked but you can then um you can
disable that disable disabled um and
then you can get unblocked note that in
a later release wave this blocking will
be
enforced. This is how it looks uh in the
UI on the web services page. If uh we
have the feature switched on, you can
see that the Microsoft owned pages are
now no longer applicable or available as
SOAP URLs. But you can also see that any
other page in in this example per tenant
extension uh is still something you can
expose as SOAP
endpoint. Um, if you turn this off,
which means you're back to the old
behavior, you still get this
notification that this will be removed.
Um, but you can still get to the SOAP
URLs in case you need to be unblocked.
In case you need to know whether any of
these pages are actually being called,
there is a new telemetry event
RT53 that gives you in which
environment, in which object, which
endpoint is being called and also the
deprecation message which in this case
is SOAP web service on UI page by
Microsoft publisher. So that will be the
the string here. And we can use this
event for
deprecating more of these
endpoints. In the reporting stack, we
added the ability to do PDF
post-processing in the context of
running a report. So there's now a new
on pre-rendering
um trigger, report trigger that allows
you to do uh these three operations. You
can append a list of PDF documents.
Maybe you want to append terms and
conditions documents to an invoice. You
can also attach a list of documents to
be embedded in a PDF, meaning that they
will be put inside the document. This is
something we expect to use for the e
invoicing feature in the base
application. And finally, you can set an
admin and or user password for the PDF
document. Something we expect to use an
uptake in the RS 1099 report in the
North America
localization. And then we added a bunch
of things for report developers. This
will just be a quick overview. There's
more details in the what's new in
reporting for developers video. For word
layouts, we added two new types of
metadata in uh the XML we embed in the
word layouts report metadata and requ
report report requests. If you open the
XML here in the developer experience in
Word, you now have this BC report
information. And if you expand that, you
see the report metadata with information
about report metadata, report name and
so on. and also the the requests when
the report was rendered. You can see
which user, which company, when it was
rendered and so on. And now you can use
these in your report. So you no need to
to code the company name, username and
so on in in the actual report data set.
You can just uh get them from here. It's
much easier for someone who looks at the
the layout. uh they they just know it's
always called company display name and
it's located
here. For Excel layouts, we added the
the ability to override the report
default for the Excel multiple worksheet
property. This allows you you can both
do this in AL and on user provided
uploaded layouts. And this allows uh for
non-breaking changes if um if you have a
report where you already have or maybe
you don't know but maybe some users
added their own layouts and assume a
certain value of Excel multiple
worksheet then you can't change that um
on the report level that would be a
breaking change but with this you can
control it on the layouts that you
control and therefore you can you can
introduce new layouts in a non-breaking
fashion. This is something we use in a
lot of the new reports that come in
manufacturing uh report layouts and uh
and reports that come in manufacturing
in version
26.1. We also made it possible to
obsolute obsolete a layout. You can do
this this either in AL with the with the
normal tags or the the normal properties
uh obsolete tag reason and uh state. But
you can also set this on uploaded uh
layouts and then this is shown on the
report layouts page. We did this because
we have this initiative of adding of
actually modernizing a lot of the
reports in the base application and
therefore some of the older layouts will
be obsoleted and this is the way we we
want to do that. On the report layouts
page uh we have new properties show
deprecated or obsolete last who who
modified or and when was this last
modified especially this is uh useful
for the user provided uploaded layouts
and uh the rest of the um properties for
a layout is something you can get or
user can get using the get info action a
new action uh in case you need to
troubleshoot something and you can ask
the user to call this and and copy the
text so you know everything about the
layout that they had an issue
with. And finally uh we added the
ability to uh validate layouts with a
new action on the report layouts page.
This uh will validate whether layouts
are okay. And uh we are also introducing
font validation in version 26. it will
just be for RDL layouts. In a later
minor update, uh we will also add this
for Word and Excel. Meaning that in case
a layout is using a font that is not
available in Business Central online or
the the the place where this is hosted,
this can now be validated.